<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2016-12-19T21:21:26+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000//</id><title type="html">Ji Haoyu’s Blog</title><subtitle>Computer Science produces fun.</subtitle><author><name>Haoyu Ji</name><email>workingjhy@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Things to Prepare for Furthering Your Education Abroad</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/tips/things-to-plan/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Things to Prepare for Furthering Your Education Abroad" /><published>2016-12-14T09:08:55+08:00</published><updated>2016-12-14T09:08:55+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/tips/things-to-plan</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/tips/things-to-plan/">&lt;aside class=&quot;sidebar__right&quot;&gt;
&lt;nav class=&quot;toc&quot;&gt;
    &lt;header&gt;&lt;h4 class=&quot;nav__title&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-file-text&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; CONTENTS&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/header&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;toc__menu&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#first-a-question-for-you&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-first-a-question-for-you&quot;&gt;First, a Question for You&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#how-determined-are-you-on-going-studying-abroad&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-how-determined-are-you-on-going-studying-abroad&quot;&gt;How determined are you on going studying abroad?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#choose-universities-and-programs&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-choose-universities-and-programs&quot;&gt;Choose Universities and Programs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#tests-to-take&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-tests-to-take&quot;&gt;Tests to Take&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#gpa&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-gpa&quot;&gt;GPA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#other-documents-required&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-other-documents-required&quot;&gt;Other Documents Required&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#how-to-improve-your-competitiveness&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-how-to-improve-your-competitiveness&quot;&gt;How to Improve Your Competitiveness&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#publications&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-publications&quot;&gt;Publications&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#internships&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-internships&quot;&gt;Internships&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#tips-for-learning-english&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-tips-for-learning-english&quot;&gt;Tips for Learning English&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#buy-books-written-in-english&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-buy-books-written-in-english&quot;&gt;Buy Books Written in English&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#chew-on-some-magazines&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-chew-on-some-magazines&quot;&gt;Chew on Some Magazines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#abandon-yourself-to-listening-english-radios&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-abandon-yourself-to-listening-english-radios&quot;&gt;Abandon Yourself to Listening English Radios&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#writing-ebook-recommendation&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-writing-ebook-recommendation&quot;&gt;Writing eBook Recommendation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a senior student in JLU, working on earning a U.S. graduate school offer right now. 
I enjoy learning English and love CS, so I chose to go abroad to further my education.
It is a big decision because there would be plenty of things you need to work on: required tests, GPAs, publications, and so forth.
To be honest, I didn’t prepare all these things very well. I made detours along the process. But I believe detours can make good lessons sometimes. So I am writing this post to share some of my ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;first-a-question-for-you&quot;&gt;First, a Question for You&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-determined-are-you-on-going-studying-abroad&quot;&gt;How determined are you on going studying abroad?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A. I am very determined.&lt;br /&gt;
B. Would like to, but not that sure.&lt;br /&gt;
C. I prefer postgraduate recommendation.&lt;br /&gt;
D. I prefer taking postgraduate entrance exams.&lt;br /&gt;
E. I prefer finding a job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For those who choose A:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It is great that you are so determined. Go on for latter parts of this post. They will be a help.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For those who choose B:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You are in the same situation as I was. My suggestion for you is- &lt;strong&gt;prepare for both A and C.&lt;/strong&gt;
It is totally possible for that both options depend largely on your major subjects’ grades. Earning a postgraduate recommendation wouldn’t be a burden if you have achieved(or you are confident on achieving) good results for many of your courses, most of which are supposed to precede the end of your Junior year.&lt;br /&gt;
You can take all required tests for studying abroad before your Senior year, which would free you for working for a postgraduate recommendation in the last summer vacation of your college life. Usually all places for recommendation would be decided by the middle of September in your Senior year. It is still OK if you didn’t take required tests before the start of your Senior year. Normally applying for a domestic graduate school is not that hard. There would still be time for you to take exams like GRE, TOEFL while earning a recommendation. (For example, most U.S. graduate schools’ application deadlines are in December or November. In that case, you would still have about 2 month for taking tests and preparing paperworks.)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For those who choose D:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Postgraduate entrance exams require extreme hard work and long-time preparing.
If you are not that optimistic about earning yourself a postgraduate recommendation, don’t hesitate to start preparing for your entrance exam. In normal cases, a no less than 5 months preparation is necessary. So plan ahead, start early, and focus on it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For those who choose E:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Directly finding a job is a thrilling option. But there are chances you change your mind in a year or two, or even after several years of working. I came to JLU with a very settled mind of looking for a job after graduation. Ironically, look where I am now.&lt;br /&gt;
If you change your mind halfway, it is totally Ok. Just take those tests needed for an admission and prepare your documents. You can apply for a graduate school at any time. (Many of my friends decided to go for further education abroad even if they had been working for many years.) &lt;strong&gt;But do note that even if you are not a student applicant, your undergraduate grades still matters.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;choose-universities-and-programs&quot;&gt;Choose Universities and Programs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To minimize the risk, you need to pick more than 6 universities or programs to apply.
While deciding which to apply, there are several things you need to concern:&lt;br /&gt;
1. &lt;strong&gt;Do I like this university?&lt;/strong&gt; (Location, History, Specilty Ranking, Housing, and so on)&lt;br /&gt;
2. &lt;strong&gt;Does this program suits me?&lt;/strong&gt; (Program Settings, Requirements, Self Interests, Scholarships, Apply Deadlines)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you select out all your options, recheck those program official sites and their admission requirements.(Documents needed for applying, tests score needed…)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tests-to-take&quot;&gt;Tests to Take&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give you a bad news, preparing for required test are usually tedious and hard. However things would be better if you do enjoy playing with English. In latter parts I will give some tips on learning English. Here let’s head back to the topic: tests.&lt;br /&gt;
There are normally two kinds of tests:&lt;br /&gt;
1. &lt;strong&gt;Language Ability Tests&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://toefl.etest.net.cn&quot;&gt;TOEFL&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ielts.etest.edu.cn&quot;&gt;IELTS&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br /&gt;
For the first category, all the tests focus on measuring test taker’s use and understand English at the university level. For expressing a specific meaning, depending on the words you choose, the sentences you write, you scores may vary. But that doesn’t mean you should always choose hard words over easy ones. Using a difficult word in a wrong way could be catastrophic. So instead of using difficult words, pick words you can manage.&lt;br /&gt;
2. &lt;strong&gt;Academic Ability Tests&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://gre.etest.net.cn/login.do&quot;&gt;GRE&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://gmat.etest.edu.cn&quot;&gt;GMAT&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lsac.org&quot;&gt;LSAT&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br /&gt;
For the second category, most tests focus on your reasoning ability, logical analysing ability, quantative ability, critical thinking skills, and so forth. In this kinds of exams, language is considered a tool for conveying your thought. So you are not likely to get a better score by doing things like replacing ‘hard-working’ with ‘assiduous’. But by improving your logical reasoning skills and practicing a lot, I am sure you can get high scores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normally, you will need to report two scores: one for language test, one for ability test. Different programs requires different tests.(For example, some requires TOEFL and GRE, others requires IELTS and GMAT). Check the official site of the program you are interested in for instructions on which test(tests) you should take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took TOEFL and GRE, if you would like to know more about these exams, you are welcomed to email me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gpa&quot;&gt;GPA&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GPA is crucial for your admission. Try your very best for every major courses. They do matters a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Different programs have different merits of calculating GPA. Sometimes one program would ask for your general GPA and your major GPA. Some programs exclude thesis courses while calculating GPA. So don’t paste the GPA given by the uims.jlu.edu.cn directly. Follow the instructions given by the program site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to give you another bad news, most programs related to computer science &lt;strong&gt;requires Major GPA&lt;/strong&gt;, which means it is &lt;strong&gt;not useful to re-enroll some elective courses, even if you get a better general GPA&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-documents-required&quot;&gt;Other Documents Required&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resume(CV)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A main accordance for knowing who you are. Refer to program sites for instructions on required details in your resume.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Personal Statement&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
An essay used for explaining why you are interested in CS(or other fields), your acquired abilities, your plans on this profession, you passion and qualities for doing research and why you pick one specific university or program.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference Letters&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Normally, a program will ask you to provide no less than 3 referees. You can ask professors you are familar with or who once taught you.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transcript&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Official or unofficial, depends on program requirements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-improve-your-competitiveness&quot;&gt;How to Improve Your Competitiveness&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;publications&quot;&gt;Publications&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Publications, if you have any, is a strength which will guarantee you an obvious advantage. Follow your tutor on some research, do whatever you can. This kind of experience sometimes can make up for some of your weakness on GPA or test scores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;internships&quot;&gt;Internships&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is better that you have conducted one intership or two. If you never conduct one, there is no need to panic. You can still receive many offers if other aspects of you application is convincing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tips-for-learning-english&quot;&gt;Tips for Learning English&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;buy-books-written-in-english&quot;&gt;Buy Books Written in English&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern novels are easier for starters. You can pick books like &lt;em&gt;Harry Potter&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Twilight&lt;/em&gt; to read. There are many stores on taobao selling imported books on reasonable prices. Don’t buy too much at one time, instead, starting with no more than 2 books. And also, try avoid reading a big tome of book, it would be extremely frustrating. When you are reading, try guessing words instead of looking them up immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;chew-on-some-magazines&quot;&gt;Chew on Some Magazines&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;half &quot;&gt;
  
    
      &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/NG.png&quot; title=&quot;National Geographic&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/NG.png&quot; alt=&quot;NG&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;/a&gt;
    
  
    
      &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/TE.png&quot; title=&quot;The Economists&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/TE.png&quot; alt=&quot;TE&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;/a&gt;
    
  
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;National Geographic &amp;amp; the Economists
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most articles in a magazine like NG is not easy to read: full of difficult words, long sentence structures, abstruse topics… However, forcing yourself to read them will definitly improve your reading ability. When you are accustomed to reading passages in NG or TE, it would make you more confident when you are faced with test reading passages. And also, if you like, try to remember some sentences in them. Your english will be improving by leaps and bounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://xmuplus.github.io&quot;&gt;The Economists Pdf Download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;abandon-yourself-to-listening-english-radios&quot;&gt;Abandon Yourself to Listening English Radios&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the application I used. You can pick any station to listen. My favorites are &lt;em&gt;the Fox News&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;NPR&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/radio.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;english radio&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;English Radio by Liang Yuan
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, iTunes can be used for listening international radios. Besides stations for talks and news, there are stations for different kinds of music. Check it out!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/itunes.png&quot; alt=&quot;itunes radio&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Radio Stations in iTunes
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;writing-ebook-recommendation&quot;&gt;Writing eBook Recommendation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On Writing Well&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://pan.baidu.com/s/1jHAgtnC&quot;&gt;Baidu Pan, Password: k35z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Haoyu Ji</name><email>workingjhy@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Some suggestions on what to expect and what to prepare for when you are considering studying abroad.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">出国留学你需要准备的事</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/tips/TTP-CN/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="出国留学你需要准备的事" /><published>2016-12-13T09:08:55+08:00</published><updated>2016-12-13T09:08:55+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/tips/TTP-CN</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/tips/TTP-CN/">&lt;aside class=&quot;sidebar__right&quot;&gt;
&lt;nav class=&quot;toc&quot;&gt;
    &lt;header&gt;&lt;h4 class=&quot;nav__title&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-file-text&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; 目录&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/header&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;toc__menu&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#section&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-section&quot;&gt;首先，有一个问题&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#section-1&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-section-1&quot;&gt;对于出国留学这件事，你非常坚定吗？&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#section-2&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-section-2&quot;&gt;选择大学和研究生项目&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#section-3&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-section-3&quot;&gt;出国考试&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#gpa&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-gpa&quot;&gt;GPA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#section-4&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-section-4&quot;&gt;其他文书&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#section-5&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-section-5&quot;&gt;如何提升竞争力&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#section-6&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-section-6&quot;&gt;论文等出版物&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#section-7&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-section-7&quot;&gt;实习经历&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#section-8&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-section-8&quot;&gt;学习英语的建议&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#section-9&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-section-9&quot;&gt;读原版书&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#section-10&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-section-10&quot;&gt;细读英语杂志&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#section-11&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-section-11&quot;&gt;听英语电台&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#section-12&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-section-12&quot;&gt;书籍推荐&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;p&gt;我是一名吉林大学大四在读生，正在申请美国研究生。对于英语，我是并不讨厌的，加之我对计算机科学也颇有兴趣，所以选择了申请国外研究生这条路。这个选择大概对我、对我的家庭而言，都是一件十分重大的事。出国申请需要准备的考试、材料很多，想要有个好的申请结果必定要下狠功夫。然而我从大二以来一直徘徊于各种选择之间，更要命鄙人凡事喜一拖再拖，所以各项准备均有所欠缺。在准备的过程里面，弯路也没少走。但可能我走的弯路，对各位也是一种提醒，所以写下了这篇短文，希望多多少少能给诸君带来一点启发。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section&quot;&gt;首先，有一个问题&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;section-1&quot;&gt;对于出国留学这件事，你非常坚定吗？&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A. 是的，我非常坚定。&lt;br /&gt;
B. 感兴趣，但并不是很确定出国是否适合自己。&lt;br /&gt;
C. 我更倾向于选择保研。&lt;br /&gt;
D. 我更倾向于考研。&lt;br /&gt;
E. 我更倾向于找工作。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;我选择了 A:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
有了决心，事情已经成功了一半！加油吧！&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;我选择了 B:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
你的处境和当时的我非常相像！我给你的建议是：同时准备出国和保研&lt;br /&gt;
出国和保研都有一个共同的指标：综合成绩（专业课成绩）。如果你至今的课程都学得不错，或者有自信认真学正在或者将要学习的课程，那么获得一个保研名额对你来说不是一件难事。软件专业大部分的课程在大三下学期结束就基本教授完毕了，这意味着在综合成绩还不错的情况下，你有充分的精力和时间去同时准备保研和出国考试或者文书准备。我的建议是在大二大三把你需要的出国考试都考完，这样在大四的保研和国外申请工作开始时，你能更加从容不迫。当然如果大三结束还没有考出国考试也没有关系，尽量争取保研名额（一般在9月份决定名单，这一般不会占用你太多的时间），利用剩余时间准备出国考试。保研工作结束以后，你还会有一段时间可以报名参加出国考试。（例如，大多数美国申请的截止日期在11、12月份，你在保研结束后还有2个多月的时间去进行考试和文书准备）&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;我选择了 D:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
考研需要非常长的准备时间和十二分的努力勤奋。 如果你的保研趋势不是非常乐观，不要犹豫，尽早开始考研的准备工作。一般来讲，考研的复习不能短于5个月，这意味着在大三结束时，你应该已经开始了紧锣密鼓的考研准备工作。如果最后你争取到了保研名额，那自然最好不过。但为了防止最坏的情况发生，尽早准备总没有错。&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;我选择了 E:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
毕业直接工作也是一个十分激动人心的事情。但是难免会有过了一两年，甚至已经工作后的一两年，改变了自己的想法的情况发生。说来有点讽刺，13年我来到吉大时，就是抱着毕业赶快找工作的想法。但最后却选择了一条偏离了很远的路。&lt;br /&gt;
如果你半路改变了你的初衷，那也没有关系。去把出国需要的考试都考完，好好准备材料，大三以后的任何一年的申请季你都可以进行网申，即使你已经工作了几年也不例外。（有时候，工作经历会成为你简历中的强项。我的很多朋友都是工作了几年后选择继续深造硕士的。）&lt;strong&gt;但是注意，尽管你是在职申请，但你的本科成绩依然非常重要，它还是申请录取时非常被看重的一项指标！&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-2&quot;&gt;选择大学和研究生项目&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;为了减少被拒绝的风险，一般你需要挑选超过6所的院校进行申请。
选择院校和研究生项目时，需要考虑的事情: &lt;br /&gt;
1. &lt;strong&gt;我喜欢这个大学吗?&lt;/strong&gt; (地理位置, 学校历史, 专业排名, 宿舍条件等)&lt;br /&gt;
2. &lt;strong&gt;这个研究生项目适合我吗?&lt;/strong&gt; (项目设置, 申请要求, 个人兴趣, 奖学金, 申请截止日期等)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;选择完院校和研究生院以后，记住官网上展示的录取要求，你在未来的准备过程中会需要它们。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-3&quot;&gt;出国考试&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;出国考试准备的过程往往漫长且艰难，并且有可能会面临多次尝试却无法提分的失望。在后面的部分我会给出一些学习英语的建议，希望它们能够帮助你享受英语，让备考不再那么痛苦。这里我们先回到话题：出国考试&lt;br /&gt;
出国考试大体分成两种：&lt;br /&gt;
1. &lt;strong&gt;语言能力考试&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://toefl.etest.net.cn&quot;&gt;TOEFL&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ielts.etest.edu.cn&quot;&gt;IELTS&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br /&gt;
这一类别，侧重于衡量你使用和理解英文的水平是否达到在国外大学学习的水准。比如在写作时，表达同一个意思，你的选词、造句都可能影响你的分数。但这并不意味着每次都要用难词代替简单词。错误地使用难词可能会导致直接的丢分。尽量选用你掌握的词来写作。&lt;br /&gt;
2. &lt;strong&gt;学术能力考试&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://gre.etest.net.cn/login.do&quot;&gt;GRE&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://gmat.etest.edu.cn&quot;&gt;GMAT&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lsac.org&quot;&gt;LSAT&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br /&gt;
这一类别，主要专注于衡量你的学术能力。在这类考试中，语言只是一种表达意思的工具。所以，类似用“assiduous”来替换“hard-working”这种做法，并不会为你带来大幅的分数提升。你需要尽量尝试提升你的逻辑能力，训练批判性的思维。如果逻辑和结构包括说理令人信服，即使你用的都是比较简单的词汇，你也能够考到一个不错的分数。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;一般你需要提供两个考试的分数：一个语言能力考试分数，一个学术能力考试分数。不同的研究生项目要求提供不同的考试成绩。具体需要进行哪些考试，你可以去研究生项目的官网进行查询。（我考了托福和GRE，如果你对这两个考试有想了解的，欢迎给我发邮件。）&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gpa&quot;&gt;GPA&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GPA对于出国申请非常重要。认真对待每一门课程，它们几乎就是一切。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;不同的研究生项目有不同的GPA计算标准，有些项目要求你提供多个GPA（综合GPA，专业GPA）。大多数院校会在GPA计算时排除非考试的课程。所以不要直接使用学校系统上给出的GPA数值。按照你的申请院校要求进行计算和填写。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;对于计算机相关专业，大多研究生院要求提供专业GPA，所以&lt;strong&gt;刷选修课绩点甚至一些基础课绩点可能并不会对你有很大帮助&lt;/strong&gt;。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-4&quot;&gt;其他文书&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;简历(CV)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
一般简历格式，具体内容参考申请院校研究生项目的网站。&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;个人陈述(PS)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
个人陈述是一篇用于陈述你的个人情况的文书。你需要在里面写明：为什么选择这个专业进行继续深造，你的学术能力怎样，未来的规划和愿景，为什么选择申请我们学校等内容。个人陈述可以不用太过于拘泥，表达好你想要表达的内容即可。&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;推荐信（RL）&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
一般会要求提供三封推荐信，你可以邀请你熟悉的老师做你的推荐人。&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;成绩单(Transcript)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
提交成绩单的细节参考申请院校的网站。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-5&quot;&gt;如何提升竞争力&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;section-6&quot;&gt;论文等出版物&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;论文是对一个人学术能力的直接证明，所以如果你能有几篇质量较高的论文发表在国内或者国际期刊上，那是再好不过的。你可以找一位你感兴趣的领域的老师，表达你希望进行研究的愿望，你将会有机会参与论文的撰写。论文有时候能够大程度弥补其他方面的短板，为你赢得一份你心仪的offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;section-7&quot;&gt;实习经历&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;一两段的实习经历也是加分项。如果你没有过实习，也不用紧张，你可以在今后多留意实习机会。或者，你可以选择用其他的长处来弥补这里的欠缺。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-8&quot;&gt;学习英语的建议&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;section-9&quot;&gt;读原版书&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;现代英文小说对于刚开始阅读原版的人来说，是一个不错的选择。它们的难度适中，情节扣人心弦。你可以选择类似《Harry Potter》, 《The Twilight》的书进行阅读。另外在某宝上也有很多价格适中的进口书专卖店，但是不要一次买太多，否则在角落落灰一定是他们的结局，这是我血与泪的教训。(我已病入膏肓，新书只读5页，大家要以我为诫)。买一到两本尝试阅读一下，读完再购买更多。同时在选购的时候，尽量避免大部头的书籍，它们往往读起来非常教人沮丧。读原著时，尽量猜测生词的意思，而不要立刻去查字典。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;section-10&quot;&gt;细读英语杂志&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;half &quot;&gt;
  
    
      &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/NG.png&quot; title=&quot;National Geographic&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/NG.png&quot; alt=&quot;NG&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;/a&gt;
    
  
    
      &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/TE.png&quot; title=&quot;The Economists&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/TE.png&quot; alt=&quot;TE&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;/a&gt;
    
  
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;National Geographic &amp;amp; the Economists
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;大多数杂志上的文章难度较高，读起来也很慢。它们的用词精确但较难，句子结构灵活多变，话题往往较为艰深… 但是，强迫自己阅读他们一定会提升你的英语水平。如果有条件，你还可以尝试背诵一些其中的内容，久而久之你的英语会突飞猛进，考试时的文章看起来都像小儿科一样。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://xmuplus.github.io&quot;&gt;The Economists Pdf Download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;section-11&quot;&gt;听英语电台&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这是我常用的英语电台软件，我较喜欢的电台是 &lt;em&gt;the Fox News&lt;/em&gt; 和 &lt;em&gt;NPR&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/radio.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;english radio&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;English Radio by Liang Yuan
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;另外，iTunes软件也可以用来听英文广播，而且其中的类别不限于新闻和谈话类，还有很多音乐类的电台。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/itunes.png&quot; alt=&quot;itunes radio&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Radio Stations in iTunes
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;section-12&quot;&gt;书籍推荐&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On Writing Well&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://pan.baidu.com/s/1jHAgtnC&quot;&gt;Baidu Pan, Password: k35z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Haoyu Ji</name><email>workingjhy@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">出国留学意味着什么？需要准备什么和注意什么？</summary></entry></feed>
